<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>english on Blogue do Caloni</title>
    <link>http://www.caloni.com.br/tags/english/</link>
    <description>Recent content in english on Blogue do Caloni</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>pt-br</language>
    <copyright>Copyright é invenção do capitalismo burguês opressor. Todos os direitos não serão reservados.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://www.caloni.com.br/tags/english/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
     
        <item>
  <title>Some things I learned in a Hacker Rank exercise</title>
  <link>http://www.caloni.com.br/hacker-rank/</link>
  <pubDate>2019-08-08</pubDate>
  
  <guid>http://www.caloni.com.br/hacker-rank/</guid>
  <description>A couple of days ago I subscribed to Hacker Hank, a website specialized in provide interview exercises. The site is as a better version of Code Jam, with the possibility to Compile &amp;amp; Run the code, as well as running several test cases.
Talking with friends about one of them proposed a interesting puzzle called Find the Running Median. This is a good problem because it is easy to understand and tricky to implement.</description>
  <details>
  
      
  
  </details>
</item>

     
        <item>
  <title>Real Programmers Don&#39;t Use Java</title>
  <link>http://www.caloni.com.br/real-programmers-dont-use-java/</link>
  <pubDate>2014-02-20</pubDate>
  
  <guid>http://www.caloni.com.br/real-programmers-dont-use-java/</guid>
  <description>When I was a newbie (and a wanna-be) I enjoyed reading &amp;ldquo;Real Programmers Don&amp;rsquo;t Use Pascal&amp;rdquo;, a satiric text that influenced and encouraged me into the path of &amp;ldquo;C/C++ enlightenment&amp;rdquo;, most even than K&amp;amp;R&amp;rsquo;s book. Since then I thought that being a &amp;ldquo;Real Programmer&amp;rdquo; was something close to everything one needs to know to get (hard) things done (quickly). Being a &amp;ldquo;Quiche Eater&amp;rdquo; was, in couterpart, comparable to nothing. Real Programmers solve real problems!</description>
  <details>
  
  </details>
</item>

     
        <item>
  <title>Using TodoList and Microsoft Project together</title>
  <link>http://www.caloni.com.br/using-todolist-and-microsoft-project-together/</link>
  <pubDate>2010-04-10</pubDate>
  
  <guid>http://www.caloni.com.br/using-todolist-and-microsoft-project-together/</guid>
  <description>The next article about bits is still in the oven. Taking vacation (40 days) had drop me out of ideas! At the moment, I can explain the tips and tricks using TodoList to manage my team and synchronize my tasks in a Microsoft Project timesheet.
The reasons why I am using TodoList are kind of obvious: it does everything I need to organize my day to day tasks and it is portable.</description>
  <details>
  
  </details>
</item>

     
        <item>
  <title>How to run anything as a service</title>
  <link>http://www.caloni.com.br/how-to-run-anything-as-a-service/</link>
  <pubDate>2008-05-27</pubDate>
  
  <guid>http://www.caloni.com.br/how-to-run-anything-as-a-service/</guid>
  <description>The biggest advantage running an application as a service, interactive or not, is to allow its start before a logon be performed. An example that happens to me is the need of debugging a GINA. In order to do this, I need the Visual Studio remote debugger be started before logon. The easiest and fastest solution is to run Msvcmon, the server part of debugging, as a service.
Today I&amp;rsquo;ve figured out a pretty interesting shortcut to achieve it.</description>
  <details>
  
  </details>
</item>

     
        <item>
  <title>MouseTool</title>
  <link>http://www.caloni.com.br/mousetool/</link>
  <pubDate>2007-11-13</pubDate>
  
  <guid>http://www.caloni.com.br/mousetool/</guid>
  <description>Well, as most of you already know, I really don&amp;rsquo;t like mice. Nevertheless I respect the users who use it and like it. That is the reason why I am writing a little more about it. This time, I going to show a program I use every day: MouseTool, for the users who does not use the mouse and like it.
The program main purpose is to avoid clicking the mouse, simulating a click every time the user stops to move the cursor.</description>
  <details>
  
      
  
  </details>
</item>

     
    
  </channel>
</rss>
